<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Finance on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/tags/finance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Finance on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/finance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mortgage calculator in R Shiny</title>
      <link>/blog/mortgage-calculator-r-shiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mortgage-calculator-r-shiny/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mortgage-calculator&#34;&gt;Mortgage calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#how-to-use-the-mortgage-calculator&#34;&gt;How to use the mortgage calculator?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#code-of-the-app&#34;&gt;Code of the app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-08-14-mortgage-calculator-in-r-shiny_files/mortgage-calculator-r-shiny-app.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently moved out and bought my first apartment. Of course, I could not pay it entirely with my own savings, so I had to borrow money from the bank. I visited a couple of banks operating in my country and asked for a mortgage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you already bought your house or apartment in the past, you know how it goes: the bank analyzes your financial and personal situation and make an offer based on your propensity to repay the bank. You then either accept the offer if you are satisfied with the rate and conditions, or visit another bank if you believe you could receive a better offer. Mortgages and loans are more complicated than that of course, but let’s keep it simple here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I kind of like to control and keep a close eye on my &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/&#34;&gt;personal finances&lt;/a&gt; (sometimes a bit too close I must admit), I knew precisely how much I could spend for my monthly mortgage repayment while still being able to cover my living expenses. However, I had no clue how much I could borrow in total for my new apartment given these housing repayments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew I was not the first person in this case, so I looked online if I could find a R script which would answer my question (and potentially also give me the total cost of the housing loan, including the loan amount and the accumulated interests). I finally found a R script created a while ago by Prof. Thomas Girke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mortgage-calculator&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mortgage calculator&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function in the script was functional and solved my main issue, but I wanted to be able to play more easily with the different settings such as the amount, the duration and the interest rate of the loan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this reason, I created a &lt;strong&gt;R Shiny app&lt;/strong&gt; which is &lt;strong&gt;available here:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/mortgage-calculator/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mortgage calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-08-14-mortgage-calculator-in-r-shiny_files/mortgage-calculator-r-shiny.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Mortgage calculator in R Shiny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I received an Excel file from a friend working in a Belgian bank which does precisely the same task. I am not an actuary nor a expert in mortgage loan, so with his file I was able to cross check the results and edit the code accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app greatly helped me to know the maximum amount I could borrow from the bank by playing with the three main settings of a mortgage, so it gave me a precise price limit when looking for apartments online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-use-the-mortgage-calculator&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to use the mortgage calculator?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you can find the mortgage calculator &lt;a href=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/mortgage-calculator/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to keep all my &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/shiny/&#34;&gt;Shiny apps&lt;/a&gt; easy to use for everyone. However, here is how to use it in case it is not intuitive enough:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the amount of the loan (i.e., the amount you would like to borrow, do not include downpayment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the annual interest rate in %&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the duration of the loan in years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the right panel (or bottom if you use the app on mobile) you will see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a summary repeating the settings you entered,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the total cost of the loan (principal and interests included), and more importantly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the amount of the monthly payments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plot representing the percentage attributed to the repayment of the interests and the capital is also displayed. You see that (especially in the first years of the loan), the higher the interest rate and the duration of the loan, the higher the percentage of the monthly repayments is attributed to the repayments of the interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the amortization table showing the remaining balance month by month is displayed after the summary and the plot. You can copy, export (in PDF, CSV or Excel) or print this amortization table for further use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;code-of-the-app&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Code of the app&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below the entire code in case you would like to enhance the app (feel free to send me your app if you happen to improve it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/AntoineSoetewey/c4cf29983f7b0695e492d53795355c4c.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I hope this &lt;a href=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/mortgage-calculator/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mortgage calculator&lt;/a&gt; helped you to play with the different settings of a mortgage, and who knows, helped you to decide which house or apartment to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclosure: Note that this application does not include investment advice or recommendations, nor a financial analysis. This application is intended for information only and you invest at your own risks. I cannot be held liable for any decision made based on the information contained in this application, nor for its use by third parties.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A practical guide on optimal asset allocation</title>
      <link>/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/optimal-asset-allocation_files/Screenshot%202020-02-04%20at%2010.36.03.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;A Shiny app with an example of optimal asset allocation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his book &lt;em&gt;A Random Walk down Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, Burton G. Malkiel advises readers of an optimal asset allocation depending on age. As an amateur investor, I thought it would be useful to develop a Shiny app which depicts his advice for other interested investors. Here is the link to the app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/optimal-asset-allocation/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Optimal asset allocation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the entire code in case you would like to enhance it (see an example on how to use this app after the embedded code):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/AntoineSoetewey/7785129a8b55ae9f9affaad2f0377690.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that the link may not work if the app has hit the monthly usage limit. Try again later if that is the case.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-use-this-app&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to use this app?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the app via this &lt;a href=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/optimal-asset-allocation/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set your age under &lt;strong&gt;How old are you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indicate how much you are willing to invest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the right panel (or below depending on the size of your screen) you will see a table and a barplot. The table includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the different type of assets which represent the different allocations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the most common tickers for each type of asset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the optimal percentage for each asset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the optimal amount for each asset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the table, the optimal percentage depends on your age (the older you are, the more conservative your portfolio), while the optimal amount depends on your age and the amount you are willing to invest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The barplot displays the optimal weight (so the optimal percentage of your portfolio) for each type of asset: stocks, bonds, real estate and cash. This is just a visualization of the column “Optimal percentage” displayed in the table above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to compare your portfolio with the optimal portfolio, as recommended by the author. For this comparison, click on the tab “Compare with your portfolio” above &lt;strong&gt;How old are you?&lt;/strong&gt;. In this tab:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Again, indicate your age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then indicate your portfolio’s value for each asset (if you do not own a specific asset, leave it equal to 0)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the right panel (or below depending on the size of your screen) you will see your portfolio’s total amount and a barplot comparing your portfolio and the optimal portfolio according to your age. This visualization will instantly give you a clear overview of what type of asset is overrepresented and underrepresented in your current portfolio compared the the optimal one. This will allow you to easily see how to rebalance your assets in accordance to what the author suggests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclosure: Note that this practical guide on asset allocation is based on the book A Random Walk down Wall Street by Burton G. Malkiel. This application does not include investment advice or recommendations, nor a financial analysis. This application is intended for information only and you invest at your own risks. I cannot be held liable for any decision made based on the information contained in this application, nor for its use by third parties.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I hope you will find this app useful to quickly replicate the optimal asset allocation suggested by Burton G. Malkiel in his book &lt;em&gt;A Random Walk down Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to have more information about this investment strategy, I suggest reading his book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>