<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shiny on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/tags/shiny/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Shiny on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/shiny/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A practial guide on optimal asset allocation</title>
      <link>/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/</guid>
      <description>In his book A Random Walk Down Wall Street, Burton G. Malkiel advises readers of an optimal asset allocation depending on age. As an amateur investor, I thought it would be useful to develop a Shiny app which depicts his advices for other interested investors. Here is the app:
 Optimal asset allocation  How to use this app? Open the app via this link Set your age under How old are you?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Draw a word cloud with a Shiny app</title>
      <link>/blog/draw-a-word-cloud-with-a-shiny-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/draw-a-word-cloud-with-a-shiny-app/</guid>
      <description>Below a Shiny app to help you draw a word cloud:
 Word cloud  Word clouds are particularily useful as part of text mining analyses. Moreover, it is also useful to analyze string and character variables for any datasets.
How to use this app?  In Word source you can see two examples of word clouds with preloaded texts. If you want to use your own file, choose the option “Upload a file” When uploading a file, make sure to upload a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to embed a Shiny app in blogdown</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>If you have developed and deployed a Shiny app and would like to embed it in blogdown, follow these steps:
create a new post as usual add runtime: shiny (and output: html_document if it is not already included) in the YAML metadata insert the following HTML code in the body of the post:  &amp;lt;iframe height=&amp;quot;800&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;100%&amp;quot; frameborder=&amp;quot;no&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/statistics-201/&amp;quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt; You should change the URL with the URL of your deployed Shiny app (after src=, do not forget that the URL should start with http:// or https:// and should be surrounded by &amp;quot;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide on how to read statistical tables</title>
      <link>/blog/a-guide-on-how-to-read-statistical-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-guide-on-how-to-read-statistical-tables/</guid>
      <description>Below a Shiny app to help you read the main statistical tables:
 Statistics-101  This Shiny app helps you to compute probabilities for the main probability distributions.
How to use this app? Open the app via this link Choose the distribution Set the paremeter(s) of the distribution (the parameters depend of course on the chosen distribution) Select whether you want to find the lower tail, upper tail or an interval Choose the value of x  On the right panel (or below depending on the size of your screen) you will see:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>