<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics by hand</title>
      <link>/blog/descriptive-statistics-by-hand/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/descriptive-statistics-by-hand/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Location versus dispersion measures Location Minimum and maximum Mean  Dispersion Range     Introduction This article explains how to compute the main descriptive statistics by hand. To learn how to compute these measures in R, read “Descriptive statistics in R”.
Descriptive statistics (in the broad sense of the term) is a branch of statistics aiming at summarizing and describing a series of values or a dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data types in R</title>
      <link>/blog/data-types-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-types-in-r/</guid>
      <description>What data types exist in R? Numeric Integer Character Logical   This article presents the different data types in R. To learn about the different variable types from a statistical point of view, read “Variable types and examples”.
What data types exist in R? There are five data types in R:
Numeric Integer Complex Character Logical  Datasets in R are often a combination of these 5 different data types.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variable types and examples</title>
      <link>/blog/variable-types-and-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/variable-types-and-examples/</guid>
      <description>Big picture Quantitative Discrete Continuous  Qualitative Nominal Ordinal  Variable transformations From continuous to discrete From quantitative to qualitative  Additional notes   This article presents the different variable types from a statistical point of view. To learn about the different data types in R, read “Data types in R”.
Big picture In statistics, variables are classified into 4 different types:
 {&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;diagram&#34;:&#34;digraph {\n\n\n\n\n \&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create an interactive booklist with automatic Amazon affiliate links in R</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-create-an-interactive-booklist-with-automatic-amazon-affiliate-links-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-create-an-interactive-booklist-with-automatic-amazon-affiliate-links-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Requirements Create a booklist Create it in Excel then import it Create it directly in R  Make it interactive Add URLs with your affiliate link to the table Extract affiliate link Append the book title and author to make it automatic Add links to the interactive table  Final result   Introduction Booklists are a useful way to share the books you have read and which you recommend to other readers and/or to promote the books you have written.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal asset allocation</title>
      <link>/blog/optimal-asset-allocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/optimal-asset-allocation/</guid>
      <description>  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data manipulation in R</title>
      <link>/blog/data-manipulation-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-manipulation-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Dataset Subset a dataset First or last observations Random sample of observations Based on row or column numbers Based on variable names Based on one or multiple criterion  Create a new variable Discretize a continuous variable  Categorical variables and labels management Recode categorical variables Change reference level  Rename variable names Create a dataframe manually Missing values Remove NAs Impute NAs    Introduction Not all datasets are as clean and tidy as you would expect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to import an Excel file in RStudio</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Transform an Excel file to a CSV file R working directory Get working directory Set working directory User-friendly method Via the console Via the text editor   Import your dataset User-friendly way Via the text editor  Import SPSS (.sav) files   Introduction As we have seen in this article on how to install R and RStudio, R is useful for many kind of computational tasks and statistical analyses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to install R and RStudio?</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>What is R and RStudio? R RStudio  The main components of RStudio Examples of code Calculator Comments Store and print values Vectors Matrices Generate random values Plot    What is R and RStudio? R R is nothing more than a programming language. At the time of writing, this language is (one of) the leading program in statistics, although not the only programming language used by statisticians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>This is the first post for the blog Stats and R, just to introduce it. This blog aims at helping academics (mainly students) and professionals (working with data) to grasp important concepts in statistics and to apply them in R.
Thanks in advance for reading. As always, if you find a mistake/bug or if you have any questions do not hesitate to let me know in the comment section of the corresponding article, raise an issue on GitHub or contact me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>