<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Chi-square test of independence by hand</title>
      <link>/blog/chi-square-test-of-independence-by-hand/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/chi-square-test-of-independence-by-hand/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hypotheses How the test works?   Introduction Chi-square tests of independence test whether two qualitative variables are independent, that is, whether there exists a relationship between the two variables of interest. In other words, this test is used to determine whether the values of one of the qualitative variables depend on the values of the other qualitative variable. If the test shows no association between the two variables (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chi-square test of independence in R</title>
      <link>/blog/chi-square-test-of-independence-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/chi-square-test-of-independence-in-r/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best addins in RStudio, or how to make your coding life easier</title>
      <link>/blog/best-addins-in-rstudio-or-how-to-make-your-coding-life-easier/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/best-addins-in-rstudio-or-how-to-make-your-coding-life-easier/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Installation Addins Esquisse Questionr Recoding factors Reordering factors Categorize a numeric variable  Blogdown    Introduction Although I have been using RStudio for several years, I only recently discovered RStudio addins. Since then, I am using these addins almost every time I use RStudio.
What are RStudio addins? RStudio addins are extensions which provide a simple mechanism for executing advanced R functions from within RStudio. In simpler words, when executing an addin (by clicking a button in the Addins menu), the corresponding code is directly sent to the console and executed without you having to write the code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create a timeline of your CV in R</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-create-a-timeline-of-your-cv-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-create-a-timeline-of-your-cv-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Minimal reproducible example How to personalize it Additional note   Introduction In this article, I show how to create a timeline of your CV in R. A CV timeline illustrates key information about your education, work experiences and extra activities. The main advantage of CV timelines compared to regular CV is that they make you stand out immediately by being visually appealing and easier to scan. It also allows you to better present your “story” by showing the chronology of your jobs and activities and thus explain how you got to where you are today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics in R</title>
      <link>/blog/descriptive-statistics-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/descriptive-statistics-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Data Minimum and maximum Range Mean Median First and third quartile Other quantiles  Interquartile range Standard deviation and variance Summary Coefficient of variation Mode Contingency table Barplot Histogram Boxplot Scatterplot QQ-plot For a single variable By groups  Density plot   Introduction This article explains how to compute the main descriptive statistics in R and how to present them graphically. To learn more about the reasoning behind each descriptive statistics, how to compute them by hand and how to interpret them, read the article “Descriptive statistics by hand”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips and tricks in RStudio and R Markdown</title>
      <link>/blog/tips-and-tricks-in-rstudio-and-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tips-and-tricks-in-rstudio-and-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>Run code Insert a comment in R and R Markdown Knit a R Markdown document Code snippets Ordered list in R Markdown New code chunk in R Markdown Reformat code Others   If you have the chance to work with an experienced programmer, you may be amazed by how fast she can write code. In this article, I share some tips and shortcuts you can use in RStudio and R Markdown to speed up the writing of your code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics by hand</title>
      <link>/blog/descriptive-statistics-by-hand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/descriptive-statistics-by-hand/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Location versus dispersion measures Location Minimum and maximum Mean Median Odd number of observations Even number of observations  Mean vs. median \(1^{st}\) and \(3^{rd}\) quartiles \(q_{0.25}\), \(q_{0.75}\) and \(q_{0.5}\) A note on deciles and percentiles  Mode Mode for qualitative variables   Dispersion Range Standard deviation Standard deviation for a population Standard deviation for a sample  Variance Variance for a population Variance for a sample  Standard deviation vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the difference between population and sample?</title>
      <link>/blog/what-is-the-difference-between-population-and-sample/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/what-is-the-difference-between-population-and-sample/</guid>
      <description>People often fail to properly distinguish between population and sample. It is however essential in any statistical anlysis, starting from descriptive statistics with different formulas for variance and standard deviation depending on whether we face a sample or a population. Moreover, the branch of statistics called inferential statistics is often defined as the science of drawing conclusions about a population from observations made on a representative sample of that population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Shiny app for inferential statistics by hand</title>
      <link>/blog/a-shiny-app-for-inferential-statistics-by-hand/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-shiny-app-for-inferential-statistics-by-hand/</guid>
      <description>Statistics is divided into two main branches:
 Descriptive statistics Inferential statistics  Descriptive statistics provide a summary of the data; it helps explaining the data in a concise way without losing too much information. Data can be summarized numerically or graphically. See descriptive statistics by hand to learn more about this branch of statistics.
Inferential statistics use a random sample of data taken from a population to make inferences, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Shiny app for simple linear regression by hand and in R</title>
      <link>/blog/a-shiny-app-for-simple-linear-regression-by-hand-and-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-shiny-app-for-simple-linear-regression-by-hand-and-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Simple linear regression is a statistical method to summarize and study relationships between two variables. When more than two variables are of interest, it is referred as multiple linear regression.
In this article, we focus only on a Shiny app which allows to perform simple linear regression by hand and in R:
 Statistics-202  For further details about what is linear regression and when it is used, please see the numerous resources on the topic available in textbooks and online.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World map of visited countries in R</title>
      <link>/blog/world-map-of-visited-countries-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/world-map-of-visited-countries-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Like me, if you like traveling as much as R you might want to draw a world map of the countries you have visited in R. Below an example with the countries I have visited as of January 2020:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A practial guide on optimal asset allocation</title>
      <link>/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/practical-guide-on-optimal-asset-allocation/</guid>
      <description>In his book A Random Walk down Wall Street, Burton G. Malkiel advises readers of an optimal asset allocation depending on age. As an amateur investor, I thought it would be useful to develop a Shiny app which depicts his advices for other interested investors. Here is the app:
 Optimal asset allocation  How to use this app? Open the app via this link Set your age under How old are you?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Draw a word cloud with a Shiny app</title>
      <link>/blog/draw-a-word-cloud-with-a-shiny-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/draw-a-word-cloud-with-a-shiny-app/</guid>
      <description>Below a Shiny app to help you draw a word cloud:
 Word cloud  Word clouds are particularily useful as part of text mining analyses. Moreover, it is also useful to analyze string and character variables for any datasets (see the different data types in R).
How to use this app?  In Word source you can see two examples of word clouds with preloaded texts. If you want to use your own file, choose the option “Upload a file” When uploading a file, make sure to upload a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to embed a Shiny app in blogdown</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>If you have developed and deployed a Shiny app and would like to embed it in blogdown, follow these steps:
create a new post as usual add runtime: shiny (and output: html_document if it is not already included) in the YAML metadata insert the following HTML code in the body of the post:  &amp;lt;iframe height=&amp;quot;800&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;100%&amp;quot; frameborder=&amp;quot;no&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/statistics-201/&amp;quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt; You should change the URL with the URL of your deployed Shiny app (after src=, do not forget that the URL should start with http:// or https:// and should be surrounded by &amp;quot;).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide on how to read statistical tables</title>
      <link>/blog/a-guide-on-how-to-read-statistical-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-guide-on-how-to-read-statistical-tables/</guid>
      <description>Below a Shiny app to help you read the main statistical tables:
 Statistics-101  This Shiny app helps you to compute probabilities for the main probability distributions.
How to use this app? Open the app via this link Choose the distribution Set the paremeter(s) of the distribution (the parameters depend of course on the chosen distribution) Select whether you want to find the lower tail, upper tail or an interval Choose the value of x  On the right panel (or below depending on the size of your screen) you will see:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data types in R</title>
      <link>/blog/data-types-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-types-in-r/</guid>
      <description>What data types exist in R? Numeric Integer Character Logical   This article presents the different data types in R. To learn about the different variable types from a statistical point of view, read “Variable types and examples”.
What data types exist in R? There are five data types in R:
Numeric Integer Complex Character Logical  Datasets in R are often a combination of these 5 different data types.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variable types and examples</title>
      <link>/blog/variable-types-and-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/variable-types-and-examples/</guid>
      <description>Big picture Quantitative Discrete Continuous  Qualitative Nominal Ordinal  Variable transformations From continuous to discrete From quantitative to qualitative  Additional notes   This article presents the different variable types from a statistical point of view. To learn about the different data types in R, read “Data types in R”.
Big picture In statistics, variables are classified into 4 different types:
 {&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;diagram&#34;:&#34;digraph {\n\n\n\n\n \&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create an interactive booklist with automatic Amazon affiliate links in R</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-create-an-interactive-booklist-with-automatic-amazon-affiliate-links-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-create-an-interactive-booklist-with-automatic-amazon-affiliate-links-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Requirements Create a booklist Create it in Excel then import it Create it directly in R  Make it interactive Add URLs with your affiliate link to the table Extract affiliate link Append the book title and author to make it automatic Add links to the interactive table  Final result   Introduction Booklists are a useful way to share the books you have read and which you recommend to other readers and/or to promote the books you have written.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data manipulation in R</title>
      <link>/blog/data-manipulation-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-manipulation-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Dataset Subset a dataset First or last observations Random sample of observations Based on row or column numbers Based on variable names Based on one or multiple criterion  Create a new variable Transform a continuous variable into a categorical variable Sum and mean in rows Sum and mean in column  Categorical variables and labels management Recode categorical variables Change reference level  Rename variable names Create a dataframe manually Missing values Remove NAs Impute NAs  Scale   Introduction Not all datasets are as clean and tidy as you would expect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to import an Excel file in RStudio</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Transform an Excel file to a CSV file R working directory Get working directory Set working directory User-friendly method Via the console Via the text editor   Import your dataset User-friendly way Via the text editor  Import SPSS (.sav) files   Introduction As we have seen in this article on how to install R and RStudio, R is useful for many kind of computational tasks and statistical analyses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to install R and RStudio?</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>What is R and RStudio? R RStudio  The main components of RStudio Examples of code Calculator Comments Store and print values Vectors Matrices Generate random values Plot    What is R and RStudio? R R is nothing more than a programming language. At the time of writing, this language is (one of) the leading program in statistics, although not the only programming language used by statisticians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>This is the first post for the blog Stats and R, just to introduce it. This blog aims at helping academics and professionals working with data to grasp important concepts in statistics and to apply them in R.
The goal of this website is to make statistics easy to understand by illustrating with examples and using plain English. When possible, for all statistical concepts covered here, I also write an article on how to apply these concepts in R.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>