<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data manipulation in RStudio</title>
      <link>/blog/data-manipulation-in-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/data-manipulation-in-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Dataset Subset a dataset Based on row or column number Based on variable names Based on one or multiple criterion  Create a new variable   Introduction Not all datasets are as clean and tidy as you would expect. Therefore, after importing your dataset into RStudio, most of the time you will need to prepare it before performing any statistical analyses. Data manipulation can even sometimes take longer than the actual analyses when the quality of the data is poor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to import an Excel file in RStudio</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Transform an Excel file to a CSV file R working directory Get working directory Set working directory User-friendly method Via the console Via the text editor   Import your dataset User-friendly way Via the text editor  Import SPSS (.sav) files   Introduction As we have seen in this article on how to install R and RStudio, R is useful for many kind of computational tasks and statistical analyses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to install R and RStudio?</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>What is R and RStudio? R RStudio  The main components of RStudio Examples of code Calculator Comments Store and print values Vectors Matrices Generate random values Plot    What is R and RStudio? R R is nothing more than a programming language. At the time of writing, this language is (one of) the leading program in statistics, although not the only programming language used by statisticians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>This is the first post for the blog Stats and R, just to introduce it. This blog aims at helping academics (mainly students) and professionals (working with data) to grasp important concepts in statistics and to apply them in R.
Thanks in advance for reading. As always, if you find a mistake/bug or if you have any questions do not hesitate to let me know in the comment section of the corresponding article, raise an issue on GitHub or contact me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>