<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Professional on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/tags/professional/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Professional on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/professional/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create a timeline of your CV in R?</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-create-a-timeline-of-your-cv-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-create-a-timeline-of-your-cv-in-r/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#minimal-reproducible-example&#34;&gt;Minimal reproducible example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#how-to-personalize-it&#34;&gt;How to personalize it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#additional-note&#34;&gt;Additional note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/how-to-construct-a-timeline-of-your-cv-in-r_files/how-to-create-a-timeline-of-your-cv.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Photo by Helloquence&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Photo by Helloquence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I show how to create a timeline of your CV in R. A CV timeline illustrates key information about your education, work experiences and extra activities. The main advantage of CV timelines compared to regular CV is that they make you stand out immediately by being visually appealing and easier to scan. It also allows you to better present your “story” by showing the chronology of your jobs and activities and thus explain how you got to where you are today. (It can also be part of your portfolio to show your R skills.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show below how to create such CV in R with a minimal reproducible example. Feel free to use the code and adapt it to you. For a more complete example (together with the code) you can check my own CV timeline &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.antoinesoetewey.com/files/CV_timeline_antoinesoetewey.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;minimal-reproducible-example&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Minimal reproducible example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the code and the result of a minimal reproducible example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/AntoineSoetewey/c6e83ad501a4b8c12b32cf9d5c06e9f9.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/how-to-construct-a-timeline-of-your-cv-in-r_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-personalize-it&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to personalize it&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to edit the example with your own academic, extra and work experiences you basically just have to edit the dataframe called &lt;code&gt;cv&lt;/code&gt; in the code above. Each row of the dataset &lt;code&gt;cv&lt;/code&gt; is a different academic program, job or activity. Rows should include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the name of the academic program, job title or activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the name of the university, school, company or workplace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the category: academic, work experience or extra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the starting date (dates must be in format &lt;code&gt;yyyy-mm-dd&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the ending date. If the role has not yet ended, type &lt;code&gt;today&lt;/code&gt; instead of the date. By using &lt;code&gt;today&lt;/code&gt; your CV timeline will automatically adapt to today’s date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add or remove a row in the dataframe if you want to add or remove a role. Indicate &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; if you do not want to specify any workplace (as it has been done for &lt;code&gt;Extra3&lt;/code&gt;). Last, do not forget to replace my name with yours for the subtitle of the timeline at the end of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experienced R users may wish to edit the &lt;code&gt;plot_timeline2&lt;/code&gt; function to their needs. However, if you are happy with the template and design of the example, you only have to change things mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;additional-note&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Additional note&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of editing the code according to your roles directly in the script, you can also create an Excel file with the required data (job title, workplace, type, start date, end date) and then &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/how-to-import-an-excel-file-in-rstudio/&#34;&gt;import it into R&lt;/a&gt;. Editing the Excel file is easier and less prone to coding errors. Moreover, if you have a long career, the code may become long while if you import the Excel file, it will always stay short and concise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I hope this article helped you to create a timeline of your CV in R. If you would like to see a more complete and live example, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.antoinesoetewey.com/files/CV_timeline_antoinesoetewey.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my timeline CV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion. If you find a mistake or bug, you can inform me by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/AntoineSoetewey/statsandr/issues&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;raising an issue on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. For all other requests, you can contact me &lt;a href=&#34;/contact/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get updates every time a new article is published by &lt;a href=&#34;/subscribe/&#34;&gt;subscribing to this blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A special thanks to Bernardo Lares for providing the first version of the code and Prof. Job N Nmadu for the suggestion about creating the file that holds the data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related articles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;//rss.bloople.net/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.statsandr.com%2Ftags%2Fr%2Findex.xml&amp;detail=-1&amp;limit=5&amp;showtitle=false&amp;type=js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>