<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/tags/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistics on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics by hand</title>
      <link>/blog/descriptive-statistics-by-hand/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/descriptive-statistics-by-hand/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Location versus dispersion measures Location Minimum and maximum Mean Median Mean vs. median  Dispersion Range     Introduction This article explains how to compute the main descriptive statistics by hand. To learn how to compute these measures in R, read “Descriptive statistics in R”.
Descriptive statistics (in the broad sense of the term) is a branch of statistics aiming at summarizing and describing a series of values or a dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide on how to read statistical tables</title>
      <link>/blog/a-guide-on-how-to-read-statistical-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-guide-on-how-to-read-statistical-tables/</guid>
      <description>Below a Shiny app to help you read the main statistical tables:
 Statistics-101  This Shiny app helps you to compute probabilities for the main probability distributions.
How to use this app? Open the app via this link Choose the distribution Set the paremeter(s) of the distribution (the parameters depend of course on the chosen distribution) Select whether you want to find the lower tail, upper tail or an interval Choose the value of x  On the right panel (or below depending on the size of your screen) you will see:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variable types and examples</title>
      <link>/blog/variable-types-and-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/variable-types-and-examples/</guid>
      <description>Big picture Quantitative Discrete Continuous  Qualitative Nominal Ordinal  Variable transformations From continuous to discrete From quantitative to qualitative  Additional notes   This article presents the different variable types from a statistical point of view. To learn about the different data types in R, read “Data types in R”.
Big picture In statistics, variables are classified into 4 different types:
 {&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;diagram&#34;:&#34;digraph {\n\n\n\n\n \&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>