<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Web on Stats and R</title>
    <link>/tags/web/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Web on Stats and R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why do I have a data science blog? 7 benefits of sharing your code</title>
      <link>/blog/7-benefits-of-sharing-your-code-in-a-data-science-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/7-benefits-of-sharing-your-code-in-a-data-science-blog/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#learn-by-writing&#34;&gt;#1 Learn by writing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#get-feedback&#34;&gt;#2 Get feedback&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#personal-note-to-remind-my-future-self&#34;&gt;#3 Personal note to remind my future self&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#contribute-to-the-open-source-community&#34;&gt;#4 Contribute to the open source community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#stay-humble-stay-curious&#34;&gt;#5 Stay humble, stay curious&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#learn-to-be-less-perfectionist-and-to-prioritize&#34;&gt;#6 Learn to be less perfectionist and to prioritize&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#build-connections-and-professional-relationships&#34;&gt;#7 Build connections and professional relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#how-to-start-your-own-blog&#34;&gt;How to start your own blog?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-09-02-why-do-i-blog-5-benefits-of-sharing-your-code_files/why-do-i-blog-5-benefits-of-sharing-your-code.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My blog &lt;a href=&#34;/&#34;&gt;statsandr.com&lt;/a&gt; was launched in December 2019. Although 9 months of writing is a very short period compared to others, I can already say that it’s been an incredible and very enriching adventure!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/&#34;&gt;45 articles&lt;/a&gt; published (at the time of writing this article) and topics ranging from &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/descriptive-statistics-in-r/&#34;&gt;descriptive statistics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/the-9-concepts-and-formulas-in-probability-that-every-data-scientist-should-know/&#34;&gt;probability&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/student-s-t-test-in-r-and-by-hand-how-to-compare-two-groups-under-different-scenarios/&#34;&gt;inferential statistics&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/r-markdown/&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/graphics-in-r-with-ggplot2/&#34;&gt;data visualization&lt;/a&gt;, I have seen many benefits of sharing my code through a technical blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I highlight 7 of them (in no particular order) with the hope that it will give ideas and incentives to some of you. In the end of this article, I also mention a couple of modern solutions needed for starting your own blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that in these 9 months, I did not make a living from my blog and this is not my goal as I would need to make it a priority.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; However, I have received enough positive feedback from readers, and more importantly, I have learned enough to continue writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;learn-by-writing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#1 Learn by writing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoy learning new stuff in many different domains. I learn (and I am still learning) a lot by teaching statistics to students from diverse backgrounds as part of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.antoinesoetewey.com/teaching/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teaching assistant&lt;/a&gt; position at university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before launching this blog, I believed that I understood a statistical concept as soon as I was able to &lt;em&gt;teach&lt;/em&gt; it to my students. If I was not able to explain it in a clear and understandable way, it meant that I needed to study it more thoroughly because I actually did not fully understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is often referred as the Feynman technique. This method of learning is based on the fact that in order to fully master a topic you need to be able to explain it back to someone in simple terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this blog, I actually realized that in order to learn and &lt;strong&gt;fully understand something new&lt;/strong&gt;, one must:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be able to clearly communicate it and teach it in simple terms,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; be able to &lt;strong&gt;write it down in a precise and concise manner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So although this blog was first launched to share statistical concepts I am most familiar with (hoping that it would be useful to some people), I now also use it to &lt;strong&gt;learn by writing&lt;/strong&gt;. I think that this additional way of learning is actually &lt;strong&gt;as powerful as teaching&lt;/strong&gt; because writing allows me to &lt;strong&gt;consolidate my understanding&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I am learning mainly about &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/statistics/&#34;&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; and its applications in &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/r/&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; as they are the main topics of the blog. However, I never thought that I would also learn so much about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;web development and SEO/analytics (which are increasingly important skills nowadays)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;project management (as you build something from scratch and wish to develop it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writing (a skill I still need to improve as a non-native English speaker)&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;communicating results (as any data scientist will tell you, results without proper communication are useless and writing a blog is a great practice)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marketing/public relation/brand management (think about social networking and how to deal with all sorts of questions from readers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining a blog teaches me essential skills that are usually taught in full-time jobs. With a blog, you are responsible of everything from the content to readers’ inquiries, similar to an employee in charge of a project and who has to deal and communicate with end users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, apart from exceptions, I do not think that a blog can completely replace a job in terms of personal development, but it definitely helps to learn a broad range of important skills. Reading books and completing data science online courses are other examples to gain skills in addition to a job, but a blog tends to be more diverse and applied, making it more beneficial (in my opinion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way I am learning is by &lt;strong&gt;doing research about the topic I am writing about&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of it is my post on &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/outliers-detection-in-r/&#34;&gt;outliers detection in R&lt;/a&gt;. As part of any &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/descriptive-statistics-in-r/&#34;&gt;descriptive analysis&lt;/a&gt;, I am used to check for potential outliers. Since I was familiar with this topic, I decided to write about it. However, I found the post not complete enough so I did some further research. It turned out that there were in fact several statistical tests that I did not know about. I wrote about these tests and I now include these new techniques whenever I check for potential outliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, I often receive emails from readers asking to write about a topic of their choice. It sometimes happens that I never heard about their suggested topic, so I do some research out of curiosity. Even if I still do not write about it because I am not familiar enough with it, at least I am aware that it exists and I know more or less what this is about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the sole benefit of learning did not convince you to start your blog, see other benefits I have experienced in the following sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;get-feedback&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#2 Get feedback&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get feedback&lt;/strong&gt;, suggestions and constructive critics &lt;strong&gt;from more experienced users&lt;/strong&gt;. Remarks greatly help in correcting typos and bugs present in my code, and they also help in improving my R skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be amazed to see that, although you spent countless hours to check your code, there will always be someone who will spot a typo that you missed. Valuable feedback from people all over the world has, for instance, definitely improved the quality and completeness of my &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/shiny/&#34;&gt;R Shiny applications&lt;/a&gt; that I use on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blog can therefore be seen as a &lt;strong&gt;powerful peer-review method&lt;/strong&gt; of your understanding of a concept, code or R practices. It is also better to make mistakes when working on a toy example and correct them, than to make mistakes on a real project at your workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, some people aggregate their blog posts into articles or books, so blogging can be seen as a way to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make incremental progress toward a longer-term publishing goal, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receive feedback at each step of this long-term goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;personal-note-to-remind-my-future-self&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#3 Personal note to remind my future self&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many times you searched for a piece of code in the folders of your computer, to finally look for the solution on Google because you could not remember for which project you wrote that piece of code? It happened to me every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With blog posts organized by &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/&#34;&gt;topics&lt;/a&gt;, it now takes me much less time (and less frustration!) to &lt;strong&gt;find code snippets that I wrote several months ago&lt;/strong&gt;. This also allows me to keep my &lt;strong&gt;code and R practices up-to-date&lt;/strong&gt;, as I only have to edit them in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of this is my article about &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/graphics-in-r-with-ggplot2/&#34;&gt;graphics in R with &lt;code&gt;{ggplot2}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I prefer plots with the &lt;code&gt;{ggplot2}&lt;/code&gt; package over plots available by default in R base, but I cannot remember all layers and their arguments. Now every time I struggle with a plot using this package, I simply revisit the corresponding article to find the solution. Same goes for many of my articles, every time I have forgotten the code or a nuance around how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could store your code in different files (&lt;a href=&#34;/blog/getting-started-in-r-markdown/&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; documents or R scripts for example, as I used to do in the past), but blog posts have the advantages that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;code snippets are highlighted, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by making it available to the world, you are forced to keep it tidy, complete and up-to-date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;contribute-to-the-open-source-community&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#4 Contribute to the open source community&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have learned so much and I keep learning everyday about R thanks to great resources made available for free by developers and scientists who believe in &lt;strong&gt;open source and free materials&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making all my code and articles freely available through a blog is in some sense, my way of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“paying back” people who helped me to learn and thanks to whom I stand where I am now, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pay in advance the many more from who I will learn in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you also believe in sharing your knowledge or expertise, having a blog is definitely a great way to &lt;strong&gt;contribute to the community&lt;/strong&gt;. Your contribution does not necessarily have to be huge, as long as it adds something, someone will use it. Remember that everyone started as a beginner, and even world experts are beginners in other domains. And you will see that as you keep sharing your knowledge with others, some people will appreciate it because they can learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I am concerned, if my small contribution is useful for some people in having a better understanding of statistics or in learning R, my goal will be reached. Others who believe passionately in a topic may want to inform people about it, in the hope that more people in turn contribute to the topic. You are totally &lt;strong&gt;free to choose the contribution&lt;/strong&gt; you want to make to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;stay-humble-stay-curious&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#5 Stay humble, stay curious&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since launching my blog, I discovered plenty of other data science blogs of high quality. The more I see new things about different topics and the more I see people doing incredible stuff, the more I realize that I actually do not know much. This reminds me to &lt;strong&gt;stay humble&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, by sharing my code with scientists from diverse backgrounds and coming from all over the world, it allows me to &lt;strong&gt;consider other perspectives&lt;/strong&gt; and practice open-mindedness, which in turn helps me to &lt;strong&gt;stay curious&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being humble and curious is, in my opinion, a good starting point to keep learning. I would not want to lose my curiosity, otherwise I may lose my appetite for learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For your information, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-bloggers.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R-bloggers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rweekly.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R Weekly&lt;/a&gt; are two great blog aggregators focusing on R, and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://towardsdatascience.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Towards Data Science&lt;/a&gt; publication on Medium is full of high quality blog posts covering many topics related to data science. Subscribe to these if you are interested in discovering more technical blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;learn-to-be-less-perfectionist-and-to-prioritize&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#6 Learn to be less perfectionist and to prioritize&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how much time you spend on your blog, remember that &lt;strong&gt;everything cannot always be perfect&lt;/strong&gt;. As a perfectionist, I cannot deny that I would love everything to run perfectly in all aspects of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing my first articles, my tendency for perfectionism was sometimes so prevalent that it was a real weakness: I could spend several minutes thinking whether a comma between two words was needed or not (which would of course make no difference at all). However, at some point, &lt;strong&gt;improving something takes so much time and energy that the added value is not as large as the added value you could create by devoting your time in producing something new&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gets even worse as you keep learning every day. As a consequence, an article which seemed to be perfect in the past may no longer be viewed as perfect today, so you want to change or add a small detail in all your previous articles. I am not saying you should not edit a blog post, it is even recommended! Nonetheless, I advise you to edit it only if it really adds a significant value to it. Otherwise, I believe it is best to spend that time and effort in creating something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a blog you will thus gradually learn to put your effort and time (which are limited resources and seem to be scarcer with the years) where it is most productive. In other words, you will learn to &lt;strong&gt;prioritize&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;build-connections-and-professional-relationships&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;#7 Build connections and professional relationships&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By sharing your practices in a specific field, you sometimes come across people who actually work on the same topic than you or have similar research interests. This was the case, among others, with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/top-r-resources-on-covid-19-coronavirus/&#34;&gt;collection of top R resources on Coronavirus&lt;/a&gt;. It started with only 5 resources, then as I was gradually adding more and more resources, Rees Morrison who was collecting blog posts on the same topic contacted me and I added his blog posts to the original collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The presentation of a R package developed by Renan Xavier Cortes which could be used to &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/a-package-to-download-free-springer-books-during-covid-19-quarantine/&#34;&gt;download free Springer books during Covid-19 quarantine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My article on the analysis of the spread of &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/covid-19-in-belgium/&#34;&gt;COVID-19 in Belgium&lt;/a&gt;, which led, in collaboration with three other researchers, to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.antoinesoetewey.com/files/slides-how-can-we-predict-the-evolution-of-covid-19-in-Belgium.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;seminar&lt;/a&gt; and the creation of graphs representing &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/covid-19-in-belgium-is-it-over-yet/&#34;&gt;COVID-19 hospital admissions in Belgium&lt;/a&gt; (which were later used by a Belgian news television channel).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These &lt;strong&gt;collaborations extended my professional network&lt;/strong&gt; and allowed me to build connections with new researchers from different universities and from different countries. I would never have known these people without first sharing my analyses on a specific topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure that a blog can lead to numerous collaborations, making the whole journey even more interesting and enriching. And who knows, the next chapter of your professional life may be shaped by one person with whom you have worked in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if your blog does not lead to any collaboration, it is still a &lt;strong&gt;great tool for self-promotion&lt;/strong&gt;. Doing some research, practicing, and writing about a topic help to become (and to be seen as) an &lt;strong&gt;expert&lt;/strong&gt; in the field. Moreover, your blog will become your &lt;strong&gt;portfolio&lt;/strong&gt; when applying for jobs or projects. Recruiters will definitely appreciate to see what you are capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether your blog is at the origin of some fruitful collaborations or a showcase of your work, it is a &lt;strong&gt;valuable asset&lt;/strong&gt; when applying for your dream job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-start-your-own-blog&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to start your own blog?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen an acceleration in my learning curve, a deeper understanding of statistics and R, and a large improvement in my communication skills since starting my blog. I never realized how useful maintaining a blog could be as a learning technique. This comes with the added benefit of being able to store information and code for myself and for others to also use, which is essential for getting feedback and connecting with other researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these 7 benefits have convinced you, the good news is that nowadays it is cheaper and easier than ever to start your own blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For non-technical blogs I recommend Medium or WordPress because it is easy to set up and it does not require code. For &lt;strong&gt;technical blogs&lt;/strong&gt;, there are plenty of &lt;strong&gt;static site generators&lt;/strong&gt; to choose from but I highly recommend using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{blogdown}&lt;/code&gt; package&lt;/a&gt; (I created my blog after reading this book). You can then host it on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and publish it using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I hope this article answered questions such as “Why do you have a blog?” or “What is the purpose of it?”, and who knows, gave you the motivation to start your own blog. If you are still undecided, I truly recommend to do it and remember that the hardest part is to start. If you are patient and passionate about a topic, you simply have to start and the rest will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I intentionally avoided to write about financial incentives in this article because I believe that it is not a good motivation to start a blog. First, many people do not make money with their blog and never will. Second, it is true that there are also a lot of people who make money with their blog, but for most of them the money is not worth the time. I see from my personal experience that a blog can sometimes be so time consuming that I would definitely make money more easily somewhere else. Moreover, as you can see, I chose not to put advertising or banner as I think that it deteriorates the reading experience (I find ads and banners extremely annoying when I see them on other blogs). This is of course my opinion it remains a matter of personal choice, and a matter of trade off: worse reading experience and more money versus better reading experience and less money. I also tend to prefer to leave the choice to readers to &lt;a href=&#34;/support/&#34;&gt;support my projects&lt;/a&gt; than to impose them ads or banners.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even native English speakers can improve their writing skills with a blog.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that I am not a programmer nor a computer scientist so I do not have extensive knowledge in creating websites. There must be many more options available but I find these options the most optimal choices given my computer skills and my goals.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to publish a Shiny app: example with shinyapps.io</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-publish-shiny-app-example-with-shinyapps-io/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-publish-shiny-app-example-with-shinyapps-io/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#prerequisite&#34;&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#step-by-step-guide&#34;&gt;Step-by-step guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#additional-notes&#34;&gt;Additional notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/coronavirus/&#34;&gt;COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; virus led many people to create interactive apps and dashboards. A reader recently asked me how to publish a &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/shiny/&#34;&gt;Shiny app&lt;/a&gt; she just created. Similarly to a previous article where I show &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/how-to-upload-r-code-on-github-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os/&#34;&gt;how to upload R code on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, I thought it would be useful to some people to see how I publish my Shiny apps so they could do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going through the different steps required to deploy your Shiny app online, you can check the final result with my apps &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/shiny/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note 1: The screenshots have been taken on MacOS and I have not tested it on Windows. Do not hesitate to let me know in the comments whether it is similar or not on other operating systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note 2: There are other ways to publish your app (with Docker for example), but the method shown below is (in my opinion) easy and works well.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;prerequisite&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shinyapps.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shinyapps.io&lt;/a&gt; platform to deploy my &lt;a href=&#34;/tags/shiny/&#34;&gt;Shiny apps&lt;/a&gt;. So in order to follow this guide you will first need to create an account (if you do not already have one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They offer a free plan, but you are limited to 5 active applications and a monthly usage of 25 active hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For your information, if you make your app available to a wide audience, expect to exceed the monthly cap of active hours quite quickly. To increase the monthly limit (or to publish more than 5 apps), you will need to upgrade your plan to a paying one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;step-by-step-guide&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Step-by-step guide&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below the steps to follow in pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 1: Open &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; and create a new Shiny app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 2: Give it a name (without space), choose where to save it and click on the Create button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 3: In the same way as when you open a new &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/getting-started-in-r-markdown/&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; document, the code for a basic Shiny app is created. Run the app by clicking on the Run App button to see the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-3.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 4: The basic app opens, publish it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-4.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 5: If it is your first Shiny app, the box “Publish From Account” should be empty. Click on “Add New Account” to link the shinyapps.io account you just created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-5.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 6: Click on the first alternative (ShinyApps.io):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 7: Click on the link to your ShinyApps account:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-7.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 8: Click on the Dashboard button to log in into your account:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-8.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 9: Click on your name and then on Tokens&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-9.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 10: If this is your first app, there should be no token already created. Create one by clicking on the Add Token button. Then Click on the Show button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-10.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 11: Click on the Show Secret button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-11.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 12: Now the code is complete (nothing is hidden anymore). Click on the Copy to clipboard button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-12.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 13: Copy the code and click on the OK button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-13.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 14: Go back to RStudio, paste the code in the console and run it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-14.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your computer is now authorized to deploy applications to your shinyapps.io account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 15: Go back to the window where you can publish your app, choose a title (without space) and click on the Publish button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-15.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 16: After several seconds (depending on the weight of your app), the Shiny app should appear in your internet browser:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-16.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 17: You can now edit the app (or replace the entire code by another of your app), and run the app again by clicking on the Run App button. For this illustration, I just added a link for more information in the side panel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-17.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 18: Check that the modifications have been taken into account (the link appears in the side panel as expected) and republish your app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-18.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 19: Click on the Publish button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-19.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 20: Your app is live! You can now share it and everyone with the link will be able to use it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-20.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;additional-notes&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Additional notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need to change the settings of your Shiny app, go to your shinyapps.io dashboard and click on the app you just created to access the settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-21.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the different settings in the tabs located at the top of the windows, and see the link to the app next to the URL field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-29-how-to-deploy-a-shiny-app-an-example-with-shinyapps-io_files/publish-shiny-app-online-shinyapps-io-22.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I hope this tutorial helped you to publish your first Shiny app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to upload your R code on GitHub: example with an R script on MacOS</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-upload-r-code-on-github-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-upload-r-code-on-github-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#prerequisite&#34;&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#step-by-step-guide&#34;&gt;Step-by-step guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#additional-notes&#34;&gt;Additional notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few days ago, a colleague asked me how to upload some R code on GitHub in order to make it accessible to everyone. Due to the lockdown, I could not just go into his office and show him on his computer. So I sent him several screenshots showing, step by step, how to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right before I deleted the screenshots I’d just taken, I thought that perhaps they would be useful for other persons, so I wrote this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note 1: The screenshots have been taken on MacOS and I have not tested it on Windows. Do not hesitate to let me know in the comments whether it is similar or not on other operating systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note 2: There must be other ways to do it, but the method shown below is (in my opinion) easy and works well.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;prerequisite&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to follow this guide and upload your R code on GitHub, you will need at least:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href=&#34;https://desktop.github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub Desktop&lt;/a&gt; application installed on your computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;step-by-step-guide&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Step-by-step guide&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this guide, I use a R script created to plot the &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/covid-19-in-belgium-is-it-over-yet/&#34;&gt;evolution of the hospital admissions due to COVID-19 in Belgium&lt;/a&gt;. See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/AntoineSoetewey/COVID-19-Figures&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;repository on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; in case you want to see the final result before proceeding further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You often hear&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A picture is worth a thousand words”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is without further ado how to upload your R script on GitHub in images:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 1: Go to github.com/login and sign in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 2: Go to your GitHub profile and create a new repository&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 3: Set the name, description, audience and README file for the new repository&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful that if you choose to make it &lt;strong&gt;public&lt;/strong&gt;, it will be &lt;strong&gt;visible to everyone&lt;/strong&gt;. If you do not want to share the code, but still want it to be uploaded on GitHub, choose the private option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initializing the repo with a README file is not mandatory, but I strongly recommend it so you will be able to add information for this repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 4: You now see your new repository with only the README file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 5: Open the GitHub Desktop application and sign in with your GitHub account&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-6.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 6 a: Clone the repository you just created on github.com to your computer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-7.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 6 b: Clone the repository you just created on github.com to your computer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-8.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 6 c: Clone the repository you just created on github.com to your computer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-9.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 7: Your new repo appears on the GitHub Desktop application&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-10.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 8: Open an R script and write your code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(See &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/how-to-install-r-and-rstudio/&#34;&gt;how to install R and RStudio&lt;/a&gt; if you are unfamiliar with it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-11.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 9 a: Save your R script in the corresponding folder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the path to the folder in step 6 c, under “Local Path”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-12.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 9 b: Save your R script in the corresponding folder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-13.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 10: Reopen GitHub Desktop, edit the commit title (1) and click on the commit button (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In step 10, make sure that the current repository (see top left) is the repo you are currently working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-14.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 11: Push the commit to github.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-15.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 12: On your GitHub profile, click on the newly created repository&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-16.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Step 13: You now see your script which has been added to the repository&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your R code is now available online via the new repository on your GitHub profile. If you need to share it, you can simply share the URL of the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;additional-notes&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Additional notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need to edit your code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-17.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Locate the folder of the repo on your computer, open the R script, edit it and save it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After your script is saved, &lt;strong&gt;do not forget to commit the changes and push the commit&lt;/strong&gt; (see step 10 above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you need to see an old version of your code, you can see all commits by clicking on the commits tab accessible via the repo on github.com:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-05-24-how-to-create-a-github-repository-for-r-scripts-on-macos_files/upload-r-code-on-GitHub-example-with-an-r-script-on-mac-os-18.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;See all commits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I hope this article helped you to create a GitHub repository, and upload your R scripts so that it is available to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to embed a Shiny app in blogdown?</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/blog/how-to-embed-a-shiny-app-in-a-r-markdown-document_files/shiny-app-in-blogdown.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have developed and deployed a Shiny app and would like to embed it in blogdown, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a new post as usual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add &lt;code&gt;runtime: shiny&lt;/code&gt; (and &lt;code&gt;output: html_document&lt;/code&gt; if it is not already included) in the YAML metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;insert the following HTML code in the body of the post:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;iframe height=&amp;quot;800&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;100%&amp;quot; frameborder=&amp;quot;no&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/statistics-201/&amp;quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should change the URL with the URL of your deployed Shiny app (after &lt;code&gt;src=&lt;/code&gt;, do not forget that the URL should start with &lt;code&gt;http://&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;https://&lt;/code&gt; and should be surrounded by &lt;code&gt;&#34;&lt;/code&gt;). Moreover, you can modify the height, the width and include or not a frame border with the corresponding tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of the result with one of my Shiny app (&lt;a href=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/statistics-201/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to the app):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe height=&#34;800&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://antoinesoetewey.shinyapps.io/statistics-201/&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that the app may not work if it has hit the monthly usage limit. Try again later if that is the case.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the entire &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; code in case you would like to use it for your own website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/AntoineSoetewey/d8c357439e6e23341ed4321d910d9181.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you encounter an issue, try loading the following packages in the body of your new post: &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;widgetframe&lt;/code&gt; (you can load a package with the command &lt;code&gt;library(widgetframe)&lt;/code&gt;). If one of the package is not installed yet, you can do it with the command &lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#34;widgetframe&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this article helped you to embed a Shiny app in your blogdown website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have a question or a suggestion related to the topic covered in this article, please add it as a comment so other readers can benefit from the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>